BARRY MURPHY

INFO

PHONE

+353868751329

EMAIL

barryrlmurphy@hotmail.com

LINKS

<u>barryrlmurphy.com</u> <u>github.com/barryrlmurphy</u> <u>linkedin.com/in/barryrlmurphy</u>

PROFILE

Javascript Engineer and Technology Leader with over 15 years of experience. I have a proven track record as an Engineer, Manager and Leader. My current role is Director of Engineering for DoneDeal.ie and Adverts.ie, the two largest classified marketplaces in Ireland.

Previously I have managed teams working on Daft.ie, Ireland's largest property marketplace. I have worked on major successful platform uplift projects, both as an engineer and manager, most notably for the DoneDeal.ie and Daft.ie platforms.

SPECIALTIES & SKILLS

Tech

Javascript(ES6), React, Next.js, MongoDB, Typescript, Jest, Node.js, Express.js, CSS(3), HTML(5), Flexbox, BEM, SASS, JSON, REST APIs, Git/Github, AngularJS, SQL, CLI, SEO, Agile Methodologies (Scrum, Kanban, Scrumban), Lean Principles, Continuous Delivery, DevOps.

Leadership

Coaching & Mentoring, Building High Performing Motivated Teams, Strategic Technical Planning, Change Management, Stakeholder Management, Hiring High Performers, Process Improvement, Project Management.

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

Director Of Engineering for DoneDeal.ie & Adverts.ie, Distilled SCH

Wexford & Dublin

Feb 2019 — Present

Responsible for people management, platform health, the output of our engineering teams and the delivery of our commercial & product goals.

My team size is currently 20+ engineers, two engineering managers and one Scrum Master. These are spread across 4 cross-functional agile delivery teams. Recently oversaw the introduction of the Scrumban methodology with two of our my largest teams which have proven to be very successful.

My typical duties in this role include:

- Ensuring our development processes are lean and effective.
- Developing the skills of all the engineers and managers on $\mbox{\it my}$ teams.
- Building motivated high performing teams.
- Working closely with the Commercial Director and Principle Product Manager to deliver our business goals.
- Strategic Technical Planning
- Ensuring the short and long term technical health of our platforms.
- Resource planning and Hiring High Performers.

Mar 2018 — Feb 2019

Responsibility for managing the Frontend, Mobile and Quality functional teams across the group (DoneDeal.ie, Adverts.ie, Daft.ie). I also supported 2 cross-functional delivery teams in the South East.

It was an exciting role as I managed 15+ engineers across multiple sites. I feel I gained a great deal of management experience in this role. It was also a technical role as I was the technical point of contact for all the engineering work that passed through the delivery teams in my location.

Frontend Engineering Manager for DoneDeal.ie & Daft.ie, Distilled SCH

Wexford & Dublin

Jan 2017 — Mar 2018

My role was extended to manage the frontend engineering effort for DoneDeal.ie and Daft.ie. I oversaw the successful merging of the DoneDeal and Daft frontend teams.

Frontend Shared Platform Project - Daft

As part of a major platform uplift project for the Daft website I oversaw all the initial planning for a new standalone frontend app. The app uses the React framework and NextJS for server side rendering. It is fully responsive and uses modern frontend best practices. The new app is now used as a starter kit for all our new frontend apps. The first version of the new site was launched in 2019.

Frontend Team Lead, DoneDeal.ie

Wexford

Jan 2014 — Jan 2017

As team lead I balanced my time between being the lead frontend developer and management responsibilities for the team. Initially I had two reports but this increased to 4 over the next two years.

My management responsibilities included 1-1s, performance reviews, training, career development and coaching. I oversaw an agile transformation with my team by introducing the use of Scrum.

One Page Place Ad Project

I was lead frontend developer on this project as well as being heavily involved in the UI design and user testing. This was the first fully responsive mobile first area of the site. It was also the first area of the site to be API driven. Over 2 million ads are placed on the site using these pages each year. I received an award from the company for my work on this project.

Jupiter Project

This project was a complete redesign of the DoneDeal website. I was lead Frontend developer on the project. I designed the frontend technical strategy for the project. The new site was fully responsive, mobile first, API driven. It was built using the AngularJS frame, SASS, Grunt, SVG icons and React for SSR. I presented at the 2015 Schibsted Tech Super Week on this project and I received an award from the company.

New Payment Pages Project

Complete redesign of the payment pages for website, fully responsive and much simpler flow. Still used every day.

Senior Frontend Developer, DoneDeal.ie

Wexford

Jun 2012 — Jan 2014

When I joined the company the Frontend areas of the site had not been updated for several years. A lot of technical debt had accumulated and there was a major productivity issue working on the Frontend of the site. Over the next couple of years

I refactored the most problematic areas, introduced minimum browser support levels, reorganised how we used our Javascript and CSS.

DoneDeal Mobile Site

Designed and built the frontend for the companies first mobile ready version of the DoneDeal website.

DoneDeal Jobs website

Designed and built the frontend for a new standalone Jobs website.

Software Developer, Nolan Transport

Wexford

Jul 2006 — Jun 2012

My role was as a fullstack PHP developer. As a fullstack developer my role required me to design and implement every aspect of new software systems for the business. Because of this I gained a lot of experience in a broad range of areas such as architect solutions, data modeling and database setup (MySQL, MS SQL Server), backend PHP, frontend javascript, server setup (Linux and Microsoft) and maintenance.

During my six years with the company I built several major software systems for the business. The two most significant systems I built were:

Transport Planning System

This system was completely built in house and is used to this day to organise the logistics of moving 350+ trucks and 1000+ trailers across Ireland, Britain and main land Europe on a daily basis. The system takes data from the GPS tracking devices on all the companies vehicles and turns this into information for the transport planners.

Timesheets System

This system is used to graph the driving time of all drivers based on their GPS data. This data is then used by the payroll system to automatically allocate weekly pay brackets for each driver. The system is still used by the company.

Field Service Engineer, TriTec Computer Support

Dublin

Jan 2005 — Jun 2006

Hardware and software support for a variety of businesses.

Production Technician, Waters Technology

Wexford

Jan 2003 — Jan 2005

As part of my role, I built a Spec Lookup System for the company on my own initiative.

I received an award from the company for my work on this system.

EDUCATION

BSc in Commercial Software Development, Waterford Institute of Technology

Waterford

Sep 1999 — May 2003

Honours Degree

Software Development, Databases, Dynamic Web Development, Software Business Management, Project Analysis & Design, Networking.

COURSES & LEARNING

Online Courses

Pluralsight: Scrum Master Skills, Building Applications with React and Redux, AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner, Being a Technology Manager Path, Understanding DevOps Path.

Frontend Masters: Intro to React, Intermediate React, State Management in Pure React

Wes Bos: Full-stack Advanced React & GraphQL, ES6 for Everyone

Udemy: The Modern React Boot-camp

Todd Motto: Ultimate Angular

barryrlmurphy.com/reading.html

Reading List

Professional Scrum Master (PSM 1), Scrum.org

Waterford

Mar 2018 — Mar 2018

CompTIA A+, Allen Technology

Wexford

Jan 2005 — May 2005

REFERENCES

References available upon request